<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://schlaich-online.de/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://schlaich-online.de/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-01-10T15:54:57+01:00</updated><id>https://schlaich-online.de/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Alexander Schlaich</title><entry><title type="html">Nanoseparated charged surfaces: nonadditivity of hydration and mean-field electrostatic repulsion</title><link href="https://schlaich-online.de/2019/01/09/pbsam/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Nanoseparated charged surfaces: nonadditivity of hydration and mean-field electrostatic repulsion" /><published>2019-01-09T17:09:55+01:00</published><updated>2019-01-09T17:09:55+01:00</updated><id>https://schlaich-online.de/2019/01/09/pbsam</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://schlaich-online.de/2019/01/09/pbsam/">&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://schlaich-online.de/assets/img/posts/pbsam_snapshot.png&quot; alt=&quot;Image&quot; style=&quot;float: right;margin-left: 7px;margin-right: 7px;margin-top: 7px;&quot; /&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The interaction between charged surfaces in water is fundamental for physical 
chemistry and biology, since basically all surfaces become charged when 
immersed in water. Experimentally measured surface interactions can be well 
described by the additive contributions of electrostatic interactions (in the 
form of Poisson-Boltzmann theory), dispersion interactions and, at nanometer 
separations, hydration repulsion. However, a stringent test of theoretical 
predictions has so far been impossible, because the surface charge density and 
the location of the surface charge is experimentally never known precisely and 
thus enter the theory as fit parameters. Such a test should in principle be 
possible with water-explicit simulations of charged surfaces, since here the 
surface charge distribution is exactly known; but keeping the water chemical 
potential fixed (which is the experimentally realized ensemble) has so far been 
difficult in simulations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://schlaich-online.de/assets/img/posts/pbsam_dens.png&quot; alt=&quot;Image&quot; style=&quot;float: left;margin-left: -40px;margin-right: 25px;margin-top: 7px;&quot; /&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the last years we have refined simulation techniques to control the water 
chemical potential &lt;a href=&quot;#schlaich_simulation_2015&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;.
In our recent paper &lt;a href=&quot;#schlaich_simulations_2018&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt; we report simulations of charged 
surfaces in the presence of monovalent counterions and water at fixed chemical 
potential and compare the resulting surface interaction pressures with 
theoretical predictions. While our simulated counterion density profiles are 
accurately described by a modified Poisson-Boltzmann approach,
the simulated interaction pressures are only for low surface 
charges described by the additive contributions of hydration and 
Poisson-Boltzmann repulsion. Already for moderately high surface charge 
densities this additivity assumption breaks down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://schlaich-online.de/assets/img/posts/pbsam_pressure.png&quot; alt=&quot;Image&quot; style=&quot;float: right;margin-left: 7px;margin-right: 7px;margin-top: 7px;&quot; /&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This we rationalize by a combination of different effects, namely, counterion
correlations as well as the surface &lt;a href=&quot;http://advances.sciencemag.org/content/4/3/eaap7415&quot;&gt;charge-induced reorientation of hydration
water&lt;/a&gt;,
which modifies the effective water dielectric constant 
&lt;a href=&quot;#schlaich_water_2016&quot;&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;.
Whereas the reduction of the water dielectric constant in confinement has recently
been &lt;a href=&quot;http://science.sciencemag.org/content/360/6395/1339&quot;&gt;confirmed experimentally&lt;/a&gt;,
a detailed analysis for charged and confined systems remains a challenging task
and is nontrivial even in &lt;a href=&quot;http://scitation.aip.org/content/aip/journal/jcp/141/21/10.1063/1.4901927&quot;&gt;bulk
electrolytes&lt;/a&gt;.
Finally, the pronounced water reorientation is expected to strongly influence the
hydration repulsion itself, revealing that the analysis of pressure-distance curves
for charged surfaces in water at nanometer separation usually is subject to a
large number of unknowns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://schlaich-online.de/assets/img/posts/pbsam_orient.png&quot; alt=&quot;Image&quot; style=&quot;float: left;margin-left: -40px;margin-right: 25px;margin-top: 7px;&quot; /&gt;
  
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;ol class=&quot;bibliography&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;post_pbsam-schlaich_simulation_2015&quot;&gt;A. Schlaich, B. Kowalik, M. Kanduč, E. Schneck, and R. R. Netz, “Simulation Techniques for Solvation-Induced Surface-Interactions at Prescribed Water Chemical Potential,” in &lt;i&gt;Computational Trends in Solvation and Transport in Liquids&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 28, G. Sutmann, J. Grotendorst, G. Gompper, and D. Marx, Eds. Jülich: Forschungszentrum Jülich GmbH, 2015, pp. 155–185. [&lt;a href=&quot;https://juser.fz-juelich.de/record/188877/files/IAS-Band-28-V2.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;WEB&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;post_pbsam-schlaich_simulations_2018&quot;&gt;A. Schlaich, A. P. dos Santos, and R. R. Netz, “Simulations of Nanoseparated Charged Surfaces Reveal Charge-Induced Water Reorientation and Nonadditivity of Hydration and Mean-Field Electrostatic Repulsion,” &lt;i&gt;Langmuir&lt;/i&gt;, Dec. 2018. [&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.langmuir.8b03474&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;WEB&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;post_pbsam-schlaich_water_2016&quot;&gt;A. Schlaich, E. W. Knapp, and R. R. Netz, “Water Dielectric Effects in Planar Confinement,” &lt;i&gt;Phys. Rev. Lett.&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 117, no. 4, p. 048001, Jul. 2016. [&lt;a href=&quot;http://link.aps.org/doi/10.1103/PhysRevLett.117.048001&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;WEB&lt;/a&gt;][&lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1103/PhysRevLett.117.048001&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;DOI&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Finally online</title><link href="https://schlaich-online.de/2018/09/17/firstpost/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Finally online" /><published>2018-09-17T17:29:55+02:00</published><updated>2018-09-17T17:29:55+02:00</updated><id>https://schlaich-online.de/2018/09/17/firstpost</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://schlaich-online.de/2018/09/17/firstpost/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It’s done!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After many years of thinking about setting up my own web-page I finally sat down and produced this page
using &lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllrb.com/&quot;&gt;jekyll&lt;/a&gt;, a static website generator.
My page is vaguely based on a scholarly template named &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/tyler-abbot/DrJekyll&quot;&gt;DrJekyll&lt;/a&gt;
which employs &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/inukshuk/jekyll-scholar&quot;&gt;Jekyll-Scholar&lt;/a&gt; plugin for nicely managing my
&lt;a href=&quot;publications/&quot;&gt;publications&lt;/a&gt; page directly from a BibTeX file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I already added a small section &lt;a href=&quot;#about&quot;&gt;about&lt;/a&gt; who I am, a detailed description of my &lt;a href=&quot;#research&quot;&gt;research&lt;/a&gt; interests
will follow soon. In my &lt;a href=&quot;#blog&quot;&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt; I will from time to time write down some exciting scientific observations,
useful code snippets or other stuff that might be worth sharing.
So hope you and I stay tuned for the next updates!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">It’s done!</summary></entry></feed>